[Evans] This is definitely a subjective question,
这绝对是一个主观的问题
and it's kind of strange that a discipline like computer science is so poorly defined
很奇怪 计算机科学这一学科定义不明确
that if you ask many computer scientists what it is you'll get very different answers.
如果你问很多计算机科学家 什么是计算机科学 你会得到非常不同的答案
But my answer to this is it is engineering, it is a science, and it's also a liberal art,
但我的答案是 它是工程、是科学、也是文科
that all 3 are true, and I'll explain why next.
所有3点都是真的 我会接下来将解释原因
This is the way I tend to think about engineering
我认为
is it's building big, complex structures that solve physical problems
工程是构建大而复杂的结构 解决物理问题
like getting cars across a bay of water.
像使车越过水湾
With that narrow view of building physical things,
有了构建物理结构的狭隘的看法
most of what we do in computing is not about building physical things,
我们在计算中做的大部分事情并不是构建物理结构
it's about building virtual things, it's about solving problems.
而是构建虚拟的事情 是解决问题
A broader view of engineering views it as design under constraint.
更广泛地看 工程是约束下的设计
When you're building a bridge, the constraints are the laws of physics.
当你正在构建一座桥梁时 约束是物理定律
You need the bridge to stand up, but you want to limit the cost of the bridge,
你需要让桥站起来 但你想要限制建桥的成本
the amount of material that you use, you want it to not sway too much in the wind.
以及使用材料的数量 你希望它在风中不会太摇摆
These are all the kinds of constraints that you have to think about in designing a bridge.
这些是你在桥梁设计时要考虑的约束
When we build computer programs, we don't usually have to worry too much
当我们创建计算机程序时 我们通常不必太担心
about the laws of physics.
物理定律
We've seen that they do affect us--that the speed it takes for light to travel
我们知道 物理定律确实会产生影响——-光速
affects how fast our programs will run--
会影响程序运行的速度——
but for the most part when we're designing programs,
但大部分时候 在设计程序时
this is not the main thing that we're thinking about.
这不是我们考虑的主要问题
The main constraint that we have to worry about is the limitations of human minds.
我们要担心的主要约束是人类思维的局限
What we can do is limited by our creativity,
我们能做的事情受创造力限制
but it's also limited by how much we can keep in mind at one time.
但它也限制于我们一次可以记住多少内容
The main tool that we have to solve this is abstraction.
我们解决此问题的主要工具是抽象
The point of abstraction is to allow us to limit what we have to keep in our mind
抽象的主要意思是让我们限制我们要牢记的内容
to be able to solve problems by hiding those details
能通过隐藏详细信息 解决问题
and thinking about things at the right level
在正确的层面上考虑事情
and designing programs in a way that we can have a procedure
设计程序 这样我们拥有的过程
that solves the problem that we want,
能够解决我们想要解决的问题
and then we can forget about the details while we move on to the next part.
然后可以忘记细节 继续到下一部分
That's all about using abstraction to overcome the limits of human minds
这就是全部有关于使用抽象 克服人类思维的限制
in terms of how much we can keep in mind and understand at one time.
克服我们一次记住和了解的内容的限制
So from that perspective, computer science is definitely about engineering.
所以从这个角度看 计算机科学绝对与工程有关
We certainly want to build things.
我们当然想建立东西
We're not building things like bridges, and we're doing that under constraints,
我们不会建立桥梁一样的东西 我们在约束下做事
but the main constraints are not from the laws of physics--
但主要制约因素并不是物理定律
because we're not building physical things--but from the limits of our own minds.
因为我们不建立物理的东西——但我们受限于人类思维
We tend to think about science as understanding nature through observation,
我们趋向于认为科学是通过观察 了解自然
and our favorite example of this is Sir Isaac Newton.
我们最喜欢的例子是艾萨克·牛顿爵士
If you can't recognize this, this is obviously Newton
如果你不认识他 这显然是牛顿
because he's sitting under an apple tree
因为他正坐在一棵苹果树下
and the probably untrue story of him understanding gravity
关于他理解重力的故事可能是不真实的
because of an apple falling on his head.
因为落在他头上的苹果
In computer science we're mostly not focused on understanding nature,
在计算机科学中 我们大多不关注了解自然
at least not in a very direct way.
至少不是通过很直接的方式
We're thinking about abstract things.
我们在考虑抽象的东西
We're writing programs to solve problems, but they're dealing with
我们在写程序来解决问题 但他们在应对
abstract representations of those problems.
这些问题的抽象代表
Certainly computing is used all over the place
当然 计算操作到处都在使用
to build better models of the universe
来建立更好的宇宙模型
and to test those models,
和测试这些模型
but that's a little different from saying that computer science itself is a science.
但这不同于说计算机科学本身是一门科学
But there is a lot of computing in nature.
但实际上很多是与计算相关的
Certainly physical processes involve computation.
当然 物理过程涉及计算
The other big example today is really in biology.
今天 另外一个典型的例子是生物学
If you think about DNA as programming organisms,
如果你认为 DNA 是生物编程
it's a very complex way of programming,
这是一个非常复杂的编程方法
but it's also very computational.
但它也是与计算息息相关的
And if you think about biology, biology is really all about computation today.
如果你想想生物学 生物学真的完全就是今天的计算
So certainly if we want to understand nature better,
如果我们想要更好地了解自然
both how human minds work--that's largely about computation--
了解人类的心灵如何工作——这很大程度上与计算相关——
and how DNA produces biological organisms
以及 DNA 怎样生成生物有机体
and how DNA evolves over time, that's really about understanding computation in nature.
DNA 是如何随着时间演变 这真的就是理解计算的性质
We didn't get to this too much in this class,
我们在课程中没有太多的涉及这一点
but this question about universality, questions about what can be computed
但是关于通用性这一问题 什么可以被计算
and how fast it can be computed are really fundamental questions about science.
计算速度多快 这样的问题真的是基本的科学问题
They are questions about our universe.
它们是和宇宙有关的问题
They are abstract questions in the sense that we can form them
它们是抽象的问题 我们可以把它们当做是
as mathematical, precise questions,
数学的问题 精确的问题
but they are also really questions about what are the limits
但它们也是关于极限是什么的问题
and what are the possibilities in our universe.
以及宇宙有什么可能性
The final correct answer was liberal art.
最后的正确答案是文科
In some sense this is arguably the easiest one to defend,
在某种意义上 这是最容易进行辩论的观点
but it's probably the one that was most surprising to many of you.
但或许是最令人惊讶的答案
Understanding why computer science is a liberal art
了解为什么计算机科学是文科
depends on actually understanding what the liberal arts are.
取决于对文科的理解
Here's a picture of the medieval view of the liberal arts.
这张图片是中世纪时对文科的看法
There's grammar, rhetoric, dialect, which we think of as logic today.
有语法、修辞、方言 我们认为是今天的逻辑
Those are the 3 that have to do with language,
这3点都和语言相关
and then there are 4 that have to do with number.
下面有4点和数字相关
The 4 that have to do with number are arithmetic, geometry, music,
即 算术、几何、音乐
which is number in time, and astronomy, which is number in time and space.
(音乐是时间的数字) 和天文 (天文是时间和空间的数字)
So how do each of those relate to computing?
这些与计算有什么关系呢？
We've certainly seen a lot with grammars.
我们当然了解了许多有关语法的知识
We've seen rules like this.
我们见过像这样的规则
Rhetoric is about using language to communicate between people,
修辞是使用语言 与人沟通
especially to persuade people.
特别是要说服人
We've actually seen rhetoric a little bit.
我们实际上也稍微了解了修辞
This is a little less clear,
这有点不太清楚
but we've seen it in terms of network protocols.
但我们在网络协议中看到了修辞
What protocols are are ways of computers communicating with each other
协议是计算机彼此进行交流的方式
and making sure that they can understand each other.
并确保它们可以相互了解
So arguably, that's a form of rhetoric.
因此可以说 这是一种修辞的形式
Logic is the art of thinking in the medieval view.
逻辑是从中世纪的视图来看 是一种思考的艺术
We've certainly used logic all over the place in this class.
我们在本课程中到处都使用了逻辑
All of our decision constructs are logical constructs,
我们的决定构造都是逻辑构造
so we've certainly used a lot of logic.
所以我们当然已使用了很多逻辑
So those are the 3 traditional liberal arts, known as the trivium, focused on language.
那些是3种传统的文科 被称作三学科 (Trivium) 注重语言
And then we have the quadrivium, which are the 4 focused on numbers.
然后我们有四学科 (Quadrivium) 注重数字
Arithmetic. We've certainly seen lots of arithmetic in this class,
算术 我们当然已经在本课程中见到了很多算术
and we can do lots of arithmetic in Python.
我们可以在 Python 中进行很多算术
Geometry. We haven't used too much directly in this class.
几何 我们在此课程中还没有过多的直接介绍
There certainly is lots of use of geometry in computing.
当然计算中也大量地使用了几何
The 2 that I'll mention most--
我会提及最最多的是两个方面
In computer graphics that's all about understanding the geometry of light
在计算机图片中 就是要足够了解光的几何结构
well enough to be able to simulate images
以模拟图像
and to be able to draw things on the screen.
并能够在屏幕上绘图
The other place where geometry comes up a lot is in networking,
另外 在网络中也经常用到了几何
and we saw that a little bit in Unit 4.
在第4单元中 我们稍微用到了几何
If we want to design a network, we care about the topology of the network--
如果我们想要设计一个网络 关心网络的拓扑——
how things are connected--and that depends on understanding geometry.
事情是如何连接的——这取决于对几何的了解
But we didn't get to either of those things too much in this class.
但我们在课程中没有过多地涉及这些内容
Music, which is about number in time.
音乐 是时间的数字
We haven't really seen how computing relates to music very much in this class,
我们在课程中 没有看到计算多大程度上与音乐相关
but certainly recursion occurs all over the place in music.
但在音乐中到处可以看到递归
If you don't believe me, I would encourage you to read this book
如果你不相信我 我鼓励你阅读这本书
by Douglas Hofstadter called Godel, Escher, Bach.
作者是道格拉斯·霍夫 被称为哥德尔、埃舍尔、巴赫
It's all about how the logic of computing relates to things in both the art of Escher
这完全是关于计算的逻辑如何与埃舍尔艺术
and the music of Bach.
以及巴赫的音乐相关的
And the final traditional liberal art was astronomy.
最后一个传统文学是天文学
We haven't seen that directly in this class either,
我们也没直接在此课程中见到的
but certainly almost all astronomy today depends on computing.
但几乎所有天文学肯定都取决于计算